Finding Aid for Ermine Cowles Case papers, 1805-1956
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ermine Cowles Case papers 1805-1956, 1920s-1940s
Case, E. C. (Ermine Cowles), b. 1871.
1 oversize folders
3.5 linear feet (in 5 boxes)
2012053 Aa2; UAl
Ermine Cowles Case was a prolific paleontologist and geologist, and a well respected professor of historical geology and paleontology at the University of Michigan. He was instrumental in the discovery and naming of several dinosaurs, and did considerable research on prehistoric vertebrates. The collection includes professional and person files that contain correspondence, organizational activities, recognitions, research, speeches, biographical records, and photographs. Inclusive dates span from 1805-1956, but most fall in the 1902s-1940s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was transferred by the Clements Library (donor no. 1333 ) on January 24, 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ermine Cowles Case (1871-1955) was a prominent American paleontologist, internationally known as one of the world's leading authorities on prehistoric life. He taught at University of Michigan from 1907-1941, and was a professor of geology and paleontology. In addition to teaching, Case was the Chairman of the Department of Paleontology and Curator of Vertebrates. He was also the Director of the Museum of Geology, and when it changed in 1928 to the Museum of Paleontology, Case became its first Director.
Case researched the scientific naming of dinosaurs and dedicated his life to filling in the fossil record of Permian and Carboniferous vertebrates from the 'red beds' of Texas, New Mexico, and Oklahoma. He also did research on stratigraphy and hominid evolution. His vast research produced several articles, monographs, and books. Because of his work, many dinosaurs were either named by him or after him.
Case was very active with paleontology and geology fieldwork. He made many discoveries, including the Brier Creek Bone Bed in Archer County, Texas, where well over 1500 specimens of separate bones were found. He also led many field parties in the western and plains states developing museum fossil collections (particularly the Paleontology Museum at University of Michigan).
In addition to traveling the United States, Case also traveled the world doing research and attending conferences, such as the International Geological Congress held in various capitols around the world. Some of his travels include locations like South America, Australia, New Zealand, Africa, Europe, and Central Asia. One of his excursions was met with the unfortunate passing of his wife, who accompanied him to Cape Town, South Africa in the early 1920s.
Despite her death, Case continued to make significant contributions to the scientific community. He was involved in many local and national organizations, clubs, and societies. He held prominent positions, such as 1929 President of the Paleontological Society of America, and representative for the Division of Geology and Geography to the National Research Council. Some other organizations he was involved with included the National Research Council, the American Society of Vertebrate Paleontologists, and the American Philosophical Society. For his contributions to these organizations and the scientific community, Case received many recognitions, awards, and honors. There is now an Ermine Cowles Case Memorial Lecture award given annually.
The records of Ermine Cowles Case span the course of his professional career, including his research, travels, and involvement in many scientific circles. Outside of academia, Case maintained correspondence with several family members and close friends, which this collection also contains. Aware of his contributions to history, Case filed away his many professional and personal correspondences noting in the first folder, "These letters are worth keeping and looking over. They contain much information of what went on, and many signatures of men active in Geology and Paleontology, both in U.S. and abroad, in my working time" (1947). Several small notes like these can be found throughout the collection among letters, photographs, and research materials. The series in this collection include: Professional Files, Personal Files, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Case, E. C. (Ermine Cowles), b. 1871.; Dinosaurs--Texas.; Fossils--Collection and presentation--Michigan.; Geology, stratigraphic--Permian.; Natural Research Council (U.S.); Paleontology.; Paleontology--Texas.; Paleontology--Carboniferous.; Paleontology--Permian.; Red beds--Oklahoma.; University of Michigan. Museum of Paleontology.; Vertibrates, Fossil--Texas.
Contributors:
Brown, Barnum.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Huene, Friederich R. Freiherr von, b. 1875.; Romer, Alfred Sherwood, 1894-1973.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional Files (1907-1952)
  The Professional Files consist of five subseries. The first subseries, which makes up a majority of the series, contains letters between Case and his colleagues, students, and other noteworthy scholars, such as Barnum Brown, William H. Hobbs, Alfred S. Romer, and Friedrich Von Huene. Correspondence pertains to expeditions, stratigraphic localities, and fossil collecting, typing, and naming. The letters are arranged alphabetically. There are also correspondences from the various geological and paleontological societies and congresses in which he was involved. Case's involvement with one of the groups, The National Research Council, makes up the second subseries. The third subseries contains recognitions given to E.C. Case, such as newspaper clippings, honors, and records of the dinosaurs that were named by, or named after him. The fourth subseries contains some of Case's research and related work, including some documentation of his foreign travels, his research on stratigraphy, and a copy of his textbook manuscript. The final subseries is a collection of speeches and talks given by Case at various events. They are sorted by event or group name.
  - Correspondence (mostly 1920s-1940s)
    - Aldrich, H.R. (Box 1)
      (includes a note from E.C. Case about the collection of professional correspondence)
    - Aldrich, J.M. (Box 1)
    - Allen, R.C. (Box 1)
    - American Express Company and Intertourist, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Amiraslanov, A. (Box 1)
    - Anderson, Amos C. (Box 1)
    - Anderson, C. (Box 1)
    - Antevs, Ernst (Box 1)
    - Arey, Albert L. (Box 1)
    - Arnold, C.P. (Box 1)
    - Augusta, Josef 1932-1935 (scattered) (Box 1)
      (letters and postcards written in German)
    - Babcock, E.B. (Box 1)
    - Bailey, E.H.S. (Box 1)
    - Baker, Horace B. (Box 1)
    - Bangs, George A. (Box 1)
    - Barbour, Erwin H. (Box 1)
    - Barbour, George B. (Box 1)
    - Barbour, Thomas (Box 1)
      (includes a photograph of a Kronosaurus skull, 1932; also a letter regarding a plesiosaurus skull and fossil restoration, August 20, 1931)
    - Barrett, Leslie P. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding geological work in Menominee Iron Range, December 21, 1920)
    - Bartlett, F.W. (Box 1)
    - Bassler, R.S. (Box 1)
    - Bastin, Edson S. (Box 1)
    - Beakeland, George (Box 1)
    - Beckwith, H. Rea (Box 1)
    - Belknap, R.L. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding his Greenland Expedition, January 8, 1933)
    - Bell, W. Charles (Box 1)
    - Berger, A. Katherine (Box 1)
    - Bergquist, S.G. (Box 1)
    - Berkey, Charles P. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter from Case requesting to make paleontology part of the science of geology, February 17, 1937)
    - Berman, A.H. (Box 1)
    - Bishop, William Warner (Box 1)
      (includes an invitation to join The Club, February 9, 1923)
    - Blackshear, Charles C. (Box 1)
    - Boonstra, L.D. (Box 1)
    - Bowden, H.R. (Box 1)
    - Bradley, Ardis (Box 1)
    - Branner, John C. (Box 1)
    - Branson, E.B. (Box 1)
    - Brigham, Edward M. (Box 1)
    - Broili, Ferdinand (Box 1)
      (includes letters in German, 1910-1927 (scattered))
    - Bronaugh, Richmond L. (Box 1)
    - Brouwer, H.A. (Box 1)
    - Brown, Barnum 1925-1942 (scattered) (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding dinosaur identification and naming, specimen localities, and fossil exchange)
    - Brown, Edward D. (Box 1)
    - Brown, N.H. (Box 1)
    - Buchanan, George S. (Box 1)
      (includes a photograph of Bob Dott, Frank Clark, Frank Greene, C.N. Gould, and several other colleagues, 1926)
    - Buettner, William. H. (Box 1)
      (includes a short biography of Buettner by Case, undated)
    - Bullard, Fred M. (Box 1)
    - Bulman, O.M.B. (Box 1)
    - Burton, M.L. 1921-1922 (Box 1)
      (includes letters regarding Case's plans to attend the International Geological Congress in Brussels; also includes letters regarding the acquisition of rare books for the Geology and Paleontology departments)
    - Butts, Charles (Box 1)
    - Camp, Charles L. (Box 1)
    - Campbell, W.W. (Box 1)
    - Condra, G.E. (Box 1)
    - Carlson, William S. (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, C.F. (Box 1)
    - Carter, T.C. (Box 1)
    - Caster, Kenneth E. (Box 1)
    - Castle, W.E. (Box 1)
    - Caufield, R.W. (Box 1)
    - Chamberlin, Rollin T. (Box 1)
    - Chamberlin, T.C. (Box 1)
    - Chaney, Ralph W. (Box 1)
    - Chang, M.S. (Box 1)
    - Cheng, Tso-Hsin (Chinese Christmas Card) (Box 1)
    - Chevalier, P.L. (Box 1)
    - Child, Charles and Lydia (Box 1)
      (includes a photograph of a tree on a home-made Christmas card, 1946)
    - Church, J.E. (Box 1)
    - Clark, H. Walton (Box 1)
    - Clark, R.W. (Box 1)
    - Clark, W.A. (Box 1)
    - Clarke, John M. (Box 1)
    - Clements, Frederic E. (Box 1)
    - Clench, William J. (Box 1)
    - Colbert, Edwin H. (Box 1)
    - Cole, Leon J. (Box 1)
    - Collier's The National Weekly (Box 1)
    - Conklin, E.G. (Box 1)
    - Cook, Harold J. (Box 1)
    - Cook, James H. (Box 1)
    - Cooke, Thorton (Box 1)
    - Coggeshall, Arthur Sterry (Box 1)
    - Croley, May Elizabeth (Box 1)
    - Croneis, Carey (Box 1)
    - Cross, Ewan P. (Box 1)
    - Curtis, Heber D. (Box 1)
    - Darton, N. H. (Box 1)
    - Davenport, Charles B. (Box 1)
    - Decker, Charles E. (Box 1)
    - Deiss, Charles F.1928-1951 (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding bone localities and expedition specimens)
    - Dempster (Christmas card, 1945) (Box 1)
    - De Stefani, Charles (Box 1)
    - De Terra, Helmut (Box 1)
    - Dice, Lee R. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding the identification of a fossil specimen, January 13, 1921)
    - Dobrovolny, Ernest (Box 1)
    - Dollo, S. (Box 1)
    - Dott, Robert H. 1926-1941 (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding Red Bed geology)
    - Doughty, George D. (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of reptile and mammoth fossils, 1930 and 1932)
    - Du Toit, Alexander (Box 1)
    - Edgeworth David, T.W. (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of a blastoid discovered by E.C. Case, 1923)
    - Edinger, Tilly (Box 1)
    - Edwards, Ira (Box 1)
    - Effinger, John R. (Box 1)
    - Efremov, J.A. (Box 1)
    - Ehlers, Jim (Box 1)
    - Eisenhart, L. P. (Box 1)
    - Eisley, Loren C. (Box 1)
    - Elias, M. K. (Box 1)
    - Elliot, William J. 1937-1943 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs and a full-size sketch of a phytosaur inter-clavical fossil; also includes letters regarding an expedition in Texas)
    - Ellsworth, Fred (Box 1)
    - Elston, Ellsworth David (Box 1)
    - Endo, Riuji (Box 1)
    - Foerste, August F. (Box 1)
    - Fallon, J. (Box 1)
    - Farnsworth, W.G. (Box 1)
    - Fenneman, Nevin M. (Box 1)
    - Fenton, Carroll Lane (Box 1)
    - Field, Richard M. (Box 1)
    - Felippone, Florentino (a business card with a note written on the back, 1925) (Box 1)
    - Finney, E.C. (Box 1)
    - Finwall, J. (Box 1)
    - Flynn, John E. (Box 1)
    - Foster, Helen (Box 1)
    - Freeman, O.W. (Box 1)
    - Fuller, P.L. (Box 1)
    - Galley, John E. (Box 1)
    - Gazin, C. L. (Box 1)
    - Geiser, S.W. (Box 1)
    - Gidley, J.W. (Box 1)
    - Gifford, E.W. (Box 1)
    - Gilbert, Walter M. (Box 1)
    - Gilmore, C. W. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding specimen classification, February 3, 1927; also includes a letter regarding reptile identification, January 25, 1939)
    - Givler, J.P. (Box 1)
    - Goddard, H. N. (Box 1)
    - Gothan, Walther (Box 1)
    - Gould, Chas N. (Box 1)
    - Gould, Laurence M. 1942-1951 (Box 1)
      (includes a photograph of pictographs etched into mudstone, 1934)
    - Greene, Frank C. (Box 1)
    - Gregory, Joseph T. (Box 1)
      (includes letters regarding Mazon Creek amphibians, expeditions for specimen collection, bird fossils, and vertebrate localities)
    - Gregory, William K. (Box 1)
    - Grobman, Arnold (Box 1)
    - Gross, W. (Box 1)
    - Haag, William G. (Box 1)
    - Haber, William (Box 1)
    - Hare, Sid J. (Box 1)
    - Harris, George G. (Box 1)
    - Hartmann-Weinberg, A. (Box 1)
    - Hastings, F. S. (Box 1)
    - Hatt, Robert T. (Box 1)
    - Haughton, Sidney H. 1919-1927 (Box 1)
      (includes letters regarding Case's trip to South Africa)
    - Hay, Oliver P. (Box 1)
    - Heald, K.C. (Box 1)
    - Herbst, H.H. (Boswell) (Box 1)
    - Herrick, C. Judson (Box 1)
    - Hickie, Paul (Christmas card) (Box 1)
    - Hill, Robert T. (Box 1)
    - Hobbs, William H. 1912-1941 (Box 1)
      (includes notes, letters, and a report regarding his travels abroad)
    - Hoffmaster, P.J. (Box 1)
    - Hollick, Arthur (Box 1)
    - Holm, Donald A. (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of tracks found in sandstone from Saudi Arabia, ca. 1947)
    - Hopier, T. (Box 1)
    - Hovey, Edmund Otis (Box 1)
    - Howell, B.F. (Box 1)
    - Hrdlicka, Ales (Box 1)
    - Huber, G. Carl (Box 1)
    - Hunt, H.R. (Box 1)
    - Hussakof, Louis (Box 1)
    - Hutchins, Harry B. (Box 1)
    - Ingalls, Philip (Box 1)
    - Jaered, Otto (Box 1)
    - Jepsen, Glen L. (Box 1)
    - Jessup, M.K. (Box 1)
    - Jillson, Willard Rouse (Box 1)
    - Johnston, C. Stuart (Box 1)
    - Jones, Clifford B. (Box 1)
    - Jones, Leland W. (Box 1)
    - Kandel, I.L. (Box 1)
    - Karpinski, Robert W. (Box 1)
    - Kelly, W.A. (Box 1)
    - Kellogg, Remington (Box 1)
    - Kelsey, Francis W. 1925-1927 (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding his field work and expeditions)
    - Keniston, Hayward (Box 1)
    - Kenoyer, L.A. (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of a petrified log from Panama)
    - Kermode, F. (Box 1)
    - Kesler, L.W. (Box 1)
    - Keydel, K. (Box 1)
    - Kleihege, J.B. (Box 1)
    - King, Roy H. (Box 1)
    - Kinsella, M.J. (Box 1)
    - Knight, S.H. (Box 1)
    - Koch, John C. (Box 1)
    - Kozary, Myron T. (Box 1)
    - Kraus, Edward H (Box 1)
    - Lambe, Lawrence M. (Box 1)
    - Lane, Alfred C. (Box 1)
    - Lane, H.H. (includes a sketch of a pelvic fossil) (Box 1)
    - Leach, W. James (Box 1)
    - Lester, Allan C. (Box 1)
    - Leverett, Frank (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding whales and whale bones, March 13, 1931)
    - Lewis, Howard B. (Box 1)
    - Lieber (Box 1)
    - Lindberg, George D. (Box 1)
    - Lindby, E.H. (Box 1)
    - Little, C.C. (Box 1)
    - Lloyd, Alfred H. (Box 1)
    - Longman, Heber A. (Box 1)
    - Longmans, W.L. (Box 1)
    - Loomis, F.B. (Box 1)
    - Loughlin, G.G. (Box 1)
    - Lozo, Frank E. (Box 1)
    - Lull, Richard S. (Box 1)
    - MacCracken., Henry (Box 1)
    - Malcolm, A.R. (Box 1)
    - Manson, Marsden 1924-1926 (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding climate evolution)
    - Martin, H.T. (Box 1)
    - Martin, Lawrence (Box 1)
    - Matthew, W.D. (Box 1)
    - Matthews, Edward B. (Box 1)
    - Mauersberger, Paul (Box 1)
    - McGrew, Paul O. (Box 1)
    - McMurray, Wilfred (Box 1)
    - McNair, Andy (Box 1)
    - Meade, Grayson E. (Box 1)
    - Mehl, M.G. (Box 1)
    - Merriam, John C. (Box 1)
      (includes several letters regarding his expedition to investigate Permian deposits in various countries, 1923)
    - Meyerhoff, Howard A. (Box 1)
    - Miller, Arthur M. (Box 1)
    - Miller, Loye H. (Box 1)
    - Miller, Paul C. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding an expedition in Texas where several fossils were found, February 17, 1919)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Monnett, V.E. (Box 1)
    - Montagu, M.F. Ashley (Box 1)
    - Montgomery, Porter (Box 1)
    - Moodie, Roy L. 1922-1932 (includes a sketch of the olecranon of an adult sabre-tooth cat; also includes letters regarding fossil anomalies, identification, age, and gender) (Box 1)
    - Moody, Paul A. (Box 1)
    - Morris, Frederick K. (Box 1)
    - Mouer, Lowell K. (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of Kansas landscapes)
    - Moy-Thomas, J.A. (Box 1)
    - Murie, O.J. (Box 1)
      (includes a letter regarding a search for fossils in Wyoming and Utah, January 1, 1928)
    - Murnaghan, Francis D. (Box 1)
    - Myers, George S. (Box 1)
    - Nelson, Theodora (Box 2)
      (includes a photograph)
    - Netting, M. Graham (Box 2)
    - Nickles, John M. (Box 2)
    - Noonan, Julia A. (Box 2)
    - Nopcsa, Baron F. (Box 2)
      (includes a letter regarding the discovery of parallel evolution of the Ornithischians and Saurischians, June 15, 1932)
    - Noyes, W.A. (Box 2)
    - Olson, John L. (Box 2)
    - O'Neill, G.D. (Box 2)
    - Orlov, J.A. (Box 2)
    - Ortenburger, A.I. (Box 2)
    - Orton, Grace L. (Box 2)
    - Osborn, Chase S. (Box 2)
    - Osborn, Henry Fairfield (Box 2)
      (includes a letter regarding the naming of bones of a vertebrate skull, September 20, 1915)
    - Ovitz, Delia G. (Christmas card unfolds to a letter, 1946) (Box 2)
    - Panniglin, F.R. (Box 2)
    - Papworth, A.G. (Box 2)
    - Pardee, Frank (Box 2)
    - Parker, W.A. (Box 2)
    - Patton, Leroy T. (Box 2)
    - Pearse, Arthur (Box 2)
    - Peterson, O.A. (Box 2)
    - Peyer, Bernard (Box 2)
      (includes several home-made stamped holiday cards, 1949 and 1952)
    - Porter, Carlos E. (Box 2)
      (includes a photograph of Dr. Porter, 1925)
    - Powers, Sidney (Box 2)
    - Praeger, William E. (Box 2)
    - Price, Paul H. (Box 2)
    - Prokes, Joseph N. (Box 2)
    - Quenstedt (faded business card with some faint writing on the back) (Box 2)
    - Redman, L.V. (Box 2)
    - Reeside, Jr., John B. (Box 2)
    - Reeves, J.S. (Box 2)
    - Richardson, Geo. H. (Box 2)
    - Richter, Rud. (Box 2)
    - Riggs, Elmer S. (Box 2)
    - Robbins, Frank Egleston (Box 2)
    - Robinson, W.I. (Box 2)
    - Roger, Austin F. (Box 2)
    - Rogers, Jr., William (Box 2)
    - Romer, Alfred S. circa 1930-1940 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding expeditions in the Red Beds of Texas and identification of fossils; includes two hand drawn maps of Archer and Baylor County, Texas, see Outsize folder UAl)
    - Roth, Robert (Box 2)
    - Rowe, J.P. (Box 2)
    - Russell, Loris S. (Box 2)
    - Ruthven, Alexander G. (Box 2)
    - Salisbury, Rollin D. (Box 2)
    - Salman, Stanley (Box 2)
    - Sanderson, Milton, W. (Box 2)
    - Saur, C.O. (Box 2)
    - Savage, J.E. (Box 2)
    - Sawin, H.J. (Box 2)
    - Sayre, A. Nelson (Box 2)
    - Schaeffer, Bob (Box 2)
    - Schmidt, M. (Box 2)
    - Schuchert, Charles (Box 2)
    - Schmeling, Belknap (Box 2)
    - Scott, D.H. (Box 2)
    - Scott, I.D. (Box 2)
    - Scott, W.B. (Box 2)
    - Sellards, E.H. (Box 2)
    - Sensenig, E.Carl (Box 2)
    - Shannon, John (Box 2)
    - Shepard, John F. and Colby, Martha G. (Box 2)
    - Sherger, W.H. (Post card with holiday wishes) (Box 2)
    - Shikama, Tokio (Box 2)
    - Shull, A. Franklin (Box 2)
    - Sieverts-Doreck, Hertha (Box 2)
    - Skeats, Ernest W. (Box 2)
    - Slosson, Edwin E. (Box 2)
    - Slusser, J.P. (Box 2)
    - Smith, Ernest Rice (Box 2)
    - Smith, George Otis (Box 2)
    - Smith, R.A. 1919-1936 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding the "Devonian problem," fossil shipments, and Michigan geology with particular reference to oil)
    - Smith, Shirley W. (Box 2)
    - Smith, Warren D. (Box 2)
    - Snider, L.C. (Box 2)
    - Snow, Leroy G. (Box 2)
    - Spinar, Zdenek (Box 2)
    - Stauffer, Clinton R. (Box 2)
    - Stechow, E. (Box 2)
    - Steere, J.B. (Box 2)
      (includes This Artificial World as Proof of the Existence of God, 1927)
    - Steere, Margaret (Box 2)
    - Stensio, Erik (Box 2)
    - Stetson, H.C. (Box 2)
    - Stevans, Edward J. (Box 2)
    - Stewart, Jr., Duncan (Box 2)
      (includes photographs of Duncan Stewart's son 1940 and 1942)
    - Strand, Embrik (Box 2)
    - Streeter, George L. (Box 2)
      (includes photographs of plaster embryo models)
    - Strauss, M. (Box 2)
    - Studer, Floyd V. (Box 2)
    - Sushkin, P. (Box 2)
    - Sussmilch, C.A. (Box 2)
    - Svihla, Arthur (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Edward H. (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Frank B. (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Ralph E. (Box 2)
    - Templin, Olin (Box 2)
    - Termier, Pierre (Box 2)
    - Thorpe, Malcolm R. (Box 2)
    - Tilton, John L. 1923-1926 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding ostracod fossils and the structure of fish bones)
    - Troxell, Edward L. 1919-1922 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding fossil exchange)
    - Twenhofel, W.H. (Box 2)
    - Udden, J.A. (Box 2)
    - Ulrich, E.O. (Box 2)
    - VanderHoof, V.L. (Box 2)
    - Van Hoepen, E.C. (Box 2)
    - Van Houten, Franklyn B. (Box 2)
    - Vaughan, T. Wayland (Box 2)
    - Vaughan, V.C. (Box 2)
    - Vaughn, Peter P. (Box 2)
    - Ver Steeg, Karl (Box 2)
    - Von Arthaber, G. (Box 2)
    - Von Engeln, O.D. (Box 2)
    - Von Huene, Friedrich 1920-1947 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding travels abroad, fossil collection, publications, and stratigraphic localities)
    - Walcott, Charles Doolittle (Box 2)
    - Walker, Bryant (Box 2)
    - Ward, Henry L. (Box 2)
    - Warthin, Jr., Aldred Scott (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding naming and filing the genus of a fossil, ca. 1926)
    - Watkins, Herbert G. (Box 2)
    - Watson, D.M.S. (Box 2)
    - Wegner, Richard N. (Box 2)
    - Weller, Stuart (Box 2)
    - Weitzel, Karl (Box 2)
    - Westoll, Thomas Stanley (Box 2)
    - Wetmore, A. (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding a fossil hawk skull, December 14, 1932 and January 12, 1934)
    - White, David (Box 2)
    - White, Errol I. (Box 2)
    - White, I.C. (Box 2)
    - White, Kirk (Box 2)
    - White, Teol E. (Box 2)
    - White, Theo (Box 2)
    - Whitney, Francis L. 1922-1931 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding bone collecting trips and expedition findings in Texas)
    - Whitney, Willis R. (Box 2)
    - Widtose, John A. (Box 2)
    - Wilkerson, Albert S. (Box 2)
    - Willard, Bradford (Box 2)
    - Wilson, Jack A. 1945-1951 (Box 2)
      (includes letters regarding fossil typing, and an expedition to Austin, Texas)
    - Winchester, Dean E. (Box 2)
    - Woodbury, Angus M. (Box 2)
    - Woods, George W. (Box 2)
    - Woodward, Arthur Smith (Box 2)
    - Woodward, R.S. (Box 2)
    - Wright, Nelda (Box 2)
    - Yoakum, C.S. (Box 2)
    - Young, Andrew (Box 2)
    - Young, Chung Chien (Box 2)
      (includes The Karakul Sheep Industry, ca. 1913)
    - Young, L.E. (Box 2)
    - Young, Stanley P. (Box 2)
    - Zangerl, Rainer (Box 2)
  - National Research Council
    - 1933 (mostly April 22) (Box 2)
    - 1934 (mostly October and November) (Box 2)
    - 1935 (mostly April 27) (Box 2)
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1938 (Box 2)
    - 1939 (Box 2)
    - 1940 (February) (Box 2)
  - Recognitions
    - Bibliography (as of April 1957) (Box 2)
    - Named Types and Specimens (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
    - Societies, Honors, and Awards (Box 2)
  - Research
    - Foreign Travel (Box 3)
    - Homonid Evolution (Box 3)
    - List of Kansas City Fossils (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Stratigraphy, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Textbook Manuscript (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Talks 1909-1947
    - American Biographical Dictionary 1934 (Box 3)